<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<study api_version="0.6">
  <id>2893</id>
  <name>Single cell gene expression patterns across different cell cycle stages in mouse embryonic cells</name>
  <active>true</active>
  <user_id>191</user_id>
  <managers>
    <manager>
      <login>ncb</login>
      <email>ncb@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Nathalie C Smerdon</name>
      <id>191</id>
    </manager>
  </managers>
  <owners>
    <owner>
      <login>knn</login>
      <email>knn@sanger.ac.uk</email>
      <name>Kedar Nath Natarajan</name>
      <id>835</id>
    </owner>
  </owners>
  <!-- Family has been deprecated -->
  <family_id></family_id>
  <created_at>2013-12-17 13:24:47 +0000</created_at>
  <updated_at>2013-12-17 13:25:18 +0000</updated_at>
  <descriptors>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study description</name>
      <value>This study is aimed to decipher the gene expression patterns that exist across the different cell cycle stages at level of individual cells and their inherent heterogeneity. Conventional studies in yeast and human cells have shown coordination between gene expression and cell-cycle. However such a study for mouse ES cells (mES) and their differentiation has not been performed at a single cell level. In this study, we obtain pure mES cells from different cell cycle stages using FACS and apply single cell RNA-sequencing using the Fluidigm C1 system. This work will decipher and unravel the transcriptional patterns that  coordinated with cell cycle progression at a single cell level.  </value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Does this study contain samples that are contaminated with human DNA which must be removed prior to analysis?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Does this study require the removal of X chromosome and autosome sequence?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Does this study require y chromosome data to be separated from x and autosomal data before archival?</name>
      <value>false</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ENA Project ID</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Abstract</name>
      <value>Progression through the cell cycle is accompanied by transcriptomic changes as cells move through the different cell cycle stages (from G1 to S to G2/M). Single cell RNA-sequencing experiments capture individual snapshots of cells at different cell-cycle stages, which are averaged in traditional bulk RNA-sequencing experiments. It is a major challenge for the interpretation of single cell RNA-sequencing data to assign individual cell-cycle states and their transcriptional signature. Being able to assign cell cycle stage is important for two reasons: (i) to remove unwanted gene expression variation due to simple cycling and (ii) to be able to discover correlations between the cell cycle and other processes, such as differentiation. We propose to address this problem by sorting cells into different cell cycle stages. This data will allow us to develop approaches to assign cell cycle stage from a pool of cells.</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Title</name>
      <value>Single cell gene expression patterns across different cell cycle stages in mouse embryonic cells</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ENA Study Accession Number</name>
      <value>ERP004534</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study Visibility</name>
      <value>Hold</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Do any of the samples in this study contain human DNA?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Are all the samples to be used in this study commercially available, unlinked anonymised cell-lines?</name>
      <value>No</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study name abbreviation</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What is the data release strategy for this study?</name>
      <value>open</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Will you be using WTSI's standard access agreement?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>How is the data release to be timed?</name>
      <value>standard</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Reason for delaying release</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Delay for</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Alignments in BAM</name>
      <value>true</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Please explain the reason for delaying release</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Comment regarding data release timing and approval</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Policy Url</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Policy title</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>EGA DAC Accession Number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>EGA Policy Accession Number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>ArrayExpress Accession Number</name>
      <value>E-ERAD-240</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Has the delay period been approved by the data sharing committee for this project?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What is the reason for preventing data release?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Has this been approved?</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Comment regarding prevention of data release and approval</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Data access group</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>SNP study ID</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>SNP parent study ID</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Number of gigabases per sample (minimum 0.15)</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>HMDMC approval number</name>
      <value></value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Study Type</name>
      <value>Transcriptome Analysis</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>What sort of study is this?</name>
      <value>transcriptomics</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Reference Genome</name>
      <value>Mus_musculus (NCBIm37)</value>
    </descriptor>
    <descriptor>
      <name>Faculty Sponsor</name>
      <value>Sarah Teichmann</value>
    </descriptor>
  </descriptors>
</study>
